Guide to the Patricia Garfinkel science policy speeches collection, 1975-2008 MS2316
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Patricia Garfinkel science policy speeches collection
1950-2007
1994-2001
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Garfinkel, Patricia
Golden, William T.
MS2316
2.5 Linear Feet 5 document boxes
This collection contains speeches, articles, and correspondence associated with the work of Patricia Garfinkel as a speech writer. The content of the speeches is science policy in the United States and is dated from 1975-2008. The articles in the second series are those used by Ms. Garfinkel during her speech writing and represent significant research materials that informed major science policy in the 1990s and early 2000s. In addition there is what is described as a manuscript by Willam T. Golden, an investment banker, a philanthropist and a main architect of American science policy in the 20th century. This manuscript more closely resembles correspondence and memos.
Arrangement
Organized into 3 series: Science policy speeches, Research files, and William T. Golden manuscript.
Separated Materials
The title A Minor Miracle an informal history of the National Science Foundation donated with the collection has been cataloged in the Special Collections stacks and is discoverable through the GW book catalog.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains speeches, articles, and correspondence associated with the work of Patricia Garfinkel as a speech writer. The content of the speeches is science policy in the United States and is dated from 1975-2008. The articles in the second series are those used by Ms. Garfinkel during her speech writing and represent significant research materials that informed major science policy in the 1990s and early 2000s. In addition there is what is described as a manuscript by Willam T. Golden, an investment banker, a philanthropist and a main architect of American science policy in the 20th century. The material within this manuscript may more reasonably be described as a collection of correspondence and memos than what many people may think of as an authored manuscript.
Biographical / Historical
Patricia Garfinkel was born in New York City. She graduated from New York University. She taught English and Geography in Montgomery County, Maryland Public Schools from 1959 to 1963. From 1963 to 1965 she lived in Paris, France and traveled extensively throughout Europe. In the early 1970s, she spent 3 years studying poetry as an independent student with poet Henry Taylor. From 1975 to 1994 she worked as a science policy analyst and speechwriter for four consecutive Chairmen of the Science and Technology Committee in the U.S. House of Representatives. From 1995 to 2012 she worked as a science policy analyst and speechwriter for four consecutive Directors and Deputy Directors of the National Science Foundation. She is listed in the Millennium Edition of Marquis' Who's Who in America. The Skeleton Dance, George Braziller, Inc., is her third book of poetry. Two previous poetry books were published by literary presses. She won a Poetry-in-Public -Places award for New York State and a Moving Words Award for Poetry on the DC Metro. She gave the first-ever poetry reading at the National Air and Space Museum in Washington, DC. She was a fellow at the Virginia Center for Creative Arts as well as President of Washington Writers Publishing House from 1994-1996. Readings include The Folger Shakespeare Library, Smithsonian Institution, Festival of the Book in Charlottesville, Virginia, Tattered Cover Books in Denver, Colorado, Praire Lights Bookstore in Iowa City, Iowa, Politics and Prose in Washinton, DC. She currently resides in Arlington, Virginia
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Patricia Garfinkel, May 20, 2013 (2013.016)
Speeches; Science; Science and state -- United States; Garfinkel, Patricia; National Science Foundation
- Science policy speeches, 1977-2007; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains speeches presented by various directors and deputy directors of the National Science Foundation and also several Chairs of the House of Representatives Science, Space and Technology Committee. These speeches date from 1977 through 2007. All speeches were written by Patricia Garfinkel in her role as speech writer for these representatives of United States science policy.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - NSF home page history, 1994-2000; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arden Bement, Director National Science Foundation, 2004-2008, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Joseph Bordogana, Deputy Director National Science Foundation [1/2], 1995-2000; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Joseph Bordogna, Deputy Director National Science Foundation [2/2], 2000-2003; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - George Brown, 4th Chairman of the House of Representatives Committee on Science, Space and Technology [1/2], 1991-1992; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - George Brown, 4th Chairman of the House of Represenatives Committee on Science, Space and Technology [2/2], 1994-1999; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - George Brown, California [1/2], 1988-1991; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - George Brown, California [2/2], 1991-1993; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rita Colwell, Director National Science Foundation, 1998-2003; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Don Fugua, Florida, 2nd Chairman House of Representatives Committee on Science, Space and Technology, 1981-1984; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Neal Lane, Director National Science Foundation and OSTP [1/3], 1994-1996; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Neal Lane, Director National Science Foundation and OSTP [2/3], 1996-1997; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Neal Lane, Director National Science Foundation and OSTP [3/3], 1995-2007; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Anne Petersen, Deputy Director National Science Foundation, 1995-1996; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Robert Roe, New Jersey, 3rd Chairman of the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology, House of Representatives, 1987-1988; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Olin Teague, Texas 1st Chairman of the House of Representatives Committee on Science, Space, and Technology, 1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Speeches by others, 1999-2004; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Research files, 1975-2005; Series 2
  Arranged alphabetically with folder titles supplied by the donor.
  This series contains copies of articles. These articles were used by Patricia Garfinkel for the writing of speeches related to science policy in the United States. These are articles self-identified by Ms. Garfinkel as being of particular importance for her work. These articles are dated 1975-2005.
  - AAU research universities, 1991-1996; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Articles - the economy 8 also IT, 1994-2001; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Biomedical / Biotechnology, anti-biotic resistence, 1998-2000; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Engineering, 1986-2001; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Edition Plaque, undated; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Emerging infectious diseases, 1985-2002; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Education, K-12, teacher training, education technology, sci + math, 1981-2002; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Environment, global warming, and public health, 1994-2001; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General -- assorted topics, 1989-2000; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Genes, G M Foods, stem cells, public health, 1999-2000; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - International -- varied topics, 1994-2000; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Physics - astronomy Fermi lab, 2001-2002; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Science / General Bill Joy, Gerald Holton Jeffesonaian Sc., 1983-2000; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Science policy, 1998-2001; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Science R and D funding [research and development funding], 1986-2001; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Scientific American revolutions in science articles, undated; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Science articles and nifty 50, 1994-2000; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Social science, 1994; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Technology, 2000-2005; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Universities - higher education, 1975-2002; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- William T. Golden manuscript, 1950-1987; Series 3
  Arranged in original order.
  This series contains what is self-identified as a manuscript by Willam T. Golden. Golden was an investment banker, a philanthropist and a main architect of American science policy in the 20th century. He died in 2007. The material within this manuscript may more reasonably be described as a group of correspondence and memos than what many people may think of as an authored manuscript.
  - Bill Golden manuscript [1/4], 1950-1987; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Bill Golden manuscript [2/4], 1950-1951; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Bill Golden manuscript [3/4], 1951; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Bill Golden manuscript [4/4], 1950-1951; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)